Hello, the Fundamentals training set in
plain language has been made available to the Frachart site for public and free use.
I hope you will pay attention to it. Hello
and greetings to you, dear friends. Good time,
I hope you are well. I am Alireza Madadhi. I
am at your service with the fourth part of the Fundamentals training set in plain language.
In the initial parts, we are trying to
have a good and understandable definition of economics.
Let's see how the economy
works. Let's understand the economy. Then we will enter into
more specialized and trading-related topics. In the
first part, I talked about the basics, why we
should learn fundamentals, why it is
important, how the Forex market works,
etc. In the second part, we talked about economic growth,
how the economy
works, the different sectors of the economy, the relationship between
producers and consumers, economic growth cycles,
recession or decline in economic growth cycles.
We came and drew a diagram
schematically showing what these cycles are like and
how they work. We called them what they are
because we need to know them because they are
talked about a lot, and we talked about the impact of
large economies. In the third part, we talked about
inflation. We talked about inflation.  How does the economic cycle
work and the types of inflation and growth cycles,
how many cycles there are, and we realized that in
each of these cycles, investors
have a different investment path, so
we need to know which cycle we are in, which cycle we are
moving towards, and the flow of
liquidity, the flow of
money
between different markets and different stock markets,
is because it changes, but in this
part we want to talk about the types of cycles in
terms of time. Explain the long-term and
short-term debt cycles, which are
very important, and from here on, there are other issues
that we are involved with in the market on a daily, quarterly,
monthly basis.
Stay with me on the fundamentals topic. Well, we
want to draw a cycle on our chart again,
but this cycle is a smooth cycle, an
upward long-term growth cycle, not
a straight line, and let's say the method always
has a certain speed, for example, we always have economic growth of 5%
per year, no, it's
not like that, this is on average,
schematically, we want to say that our goal is that the
economy is growing in the long term, that is,
economies over time  They will grow bigger, they
will have economic growth.
Compare the current economies with the last 100 years, the last 50 years. Compare the economy before mechanization
with the present. How much
bigger is the economy now? So in the long run,
kids, what are the reasons why the economy is growing and getting stronger? The
reasons for this growth are that we
have increased knowledge. For example, technology,
electricity, the invention of
machines, which simplify a lot of work in industry.
All of these things cause
production capacity to increase and growth to occur.
We have an increase in population over time in
general, which causes
aggregate demand to increase. When aggregate demand increases,
more production is also needed. The
second thing is the increase in interest rates.
Again, the growth that we can have in the supply
and the increase in living standards.
Over time, you have living standards
that have constantly increased and
risen, and that is one of the reasons for growth. So in the
long run, we are talking about 220 years, 30 years
above these numbers. In the long
run, we have a growth cycle and
economies move forward. They
will have economic growth on average, but
we also have two other cycles.  We have the long-
term and short-term debt cycles, which
are important topics, and in this section we want to
talk about these two cycles and
how these cycles come into being and
how they work. In the first slide, I just
want to tell you how long each of these cycles takes to
form and what their periods are
like. In the long-
term cycles, which is our white line, we have 50 years of
economic growth. In the long-term debt cycle,
which is not to mention the pink line, we
have 50 years of very good economic growth. Or you
could call it De Loring, or we could say
that if we want to look at it from the perspective of debt or credit.
Now I'll tell you what debt and
credit are. If we want to look at it from the perspective of debt and credit, it
means that debt and
credit are increasing. Then there is a
period of 10 to 15 years, which is much smaller than the
Leverage period, which is the period of increasing debt. We
have the De Loring period, which means that the
bubble that has formed in the debt issue
usually deflates in two to three years, and then
we have a recovery period, when the economy is
growing again or after that.  It's on the Loring path,
meaning we're going to get back to that
point of economic growth, our economic growth,
guys, so let's consider this period, an
average period of 60 years, 70
years that occurs in economies.
For example, 2008
was where our long-term debt crisis
happened, meaning the economy
recorded significant economic growth over several decades. In
2008, we had a deep crisis. Or let's go
back to 1930, which is called the Great Depression. You've
probably heard of it. There, too, we
had a period of Deal Vision. This period of
Deal Vision, or the reduction of debt, the reduction of
credit in the economy, is an extremely difficult period for the
economy. We're not talking about the reduction of economic growth
here. In previous discussions,
previous videos, everything
I said about economic growth is related to a
short period in this cycle. For example,
consider this part, what it's like. Let me
use my pen.
Consider this part. We had this cycle.
We were talking about it in previous parts,
which is in the middle of a long-term cycle.
Which long-term cycle is this cycle
that is marked with a white line? The
Dale Vision era, guys, is a very difficult period,
meaning a very deep recession where
consumers are under a lot of pressure. Governments
are under pressure. You could even say that there is a
possibility of the social and political atmosphere
in the country collapsing. It is a very difficult period. I
want to say that the previous cycles that I
explained to you
are different. We have a decline in economic growth here, for example,
but this is different from the Dale
Vision era, where we are witnessing a sharp decline in
economic growth. Now let's move on to the
next topics. I will explain to you more in more detail.
Here you
can see the economic cycle of the United States from
1947 to the present. There is a
chart of the US GDP and we
have zero. When
the chart is above this number, it means that we
had economic growth, meaning that the economy grew.
But during this same
period of growth, for example, look at this period.
From 1960 to
1983,
our economic growth was positive, but there
was a period when economic growth was very good and was on the
rise. Then a period of decline occurred,
meaning that the same cycle has formed here again.  The
economy got stronger, then it slowed down again, then it got stronger, then it got stronger,
but in 2008
we had a very significant decline in the economy
and economic growth fell below zero.
Guys, whenever economic growth falls below zero, we
call it deleveraging, or the
very severe recessions that
happen. So guys, we
have a short-term cycle, for example, here you can
see these cycles: growth, decline, growth,
decline, growth, decline, but we have a series of
cycles that form in the long term, the
long-term debt cycle of the Deal Origin era, when
conditions become very difficult. So in the middle of the picture, we
have a table that says how the
economic growth was, how many years it lasted, how
many months it lasted, for example, from 11:30,
1945 to 10:31,
1948,
we had 35 months of economic growth or expansion,
and it says what the different periods are
like. It takes an average and says
that the
maximum is an expansion period of 11 months, the
minimum is 10 months, meaning that
our growth period is from 10 to 118 months, and on
average it lasts 61 months, or 5.  The year
that I brought you in the previous slide,
our economic growth period lasts 5 years or 60 61 months, but guys, our long-term
debt cycle, which I said, we enter extremely
severe recessions, usually periods of 70 years or 80
years have happened, for example, in the United States in
1930, then came 2008, about 80 years later,
or for example, in Japan in 1990, we
saw that decade of significant economic growth decline,
or the Delors era in the Japanese economy.
So we have two types of cycles. We must be
aware of recessions. When we are talking about recessions
in
economies, we are talking about, for example, 2008. We
must know
what increase and what decrease in economic growth
occurred in 2008. For example, in 2008, you
see this decline. Then the
economy recovers, grows, and
then, for example, in 2015-16, we had a period of
economic growth decline here, but
everyone talks about that 2078,
what happened in the economy? We call this period a
growth decline, but  We call this period the
economic recession or deleveraging.
Now we come to the topic of credit. It is very important. It is
extremely important. It affects
our trading in market fluctuations and trends.
Be very careful
about this and listen carefully. So
what is credit? Credit or
debt. We can also call it debt. Credit
or debt. Guys, I want to
tell you simply. It is the money that banks are
lending to consumers or to the economy. Credit
means a loan. It is the loan
that the bank is paying.
You go to the bank and show collateral.
For example, you pledge your blood document and
receive a loan on that document.
We call this credit or credit in the economy. And these
guys create
a different amount of this credit with real money. The
banks create this credit.
And how much is it? The amount of loans in the
economy depends on different elements. It
depends on the conditions in the
economy. But it can be said that the milk of
credit or credit is in the hands of the banks. To
what extent?  Okay, but
we can say that credit is the same loan that people are getting
from banks. We all
took it.
We get some money from the bank.
We put up a security called collateral. Or you can say, we
put up a guarantor. Now, that security can
be a person, his salary, or any form. Anyway,
here the bank takes a security
and pays you a loan.
During the repayment period, you have to
return the principal plus interest. We are just going to
start discussing the interest rate here.
So, you
guys receive a loan from the bank.
Then you have to make monthly repayments.
Now,
you pay the principal plus interest to the bank.
For example, the bank considers a rate of 20%
or a rate of 15%
as its profit during the
repayment period. So, you
pay this amount of interest to the bank.
We have all kinds of loans,
which kids don't care much. For example, we
have a loan that is paid off at the end of the term, or for
example, we have a loan that is paid off at
the end of the term, and the
borrower pays the interest at once. We have all kinds of loans,
but I don't want to make it difficult
for you guys. We can say that it does
n't matter to us what the loan is like now. The loan that is being given
in the
economy is given to the consumer and the
borrower. It doesn't matter how it is repaid, what it is
called. In general, the money that banks
create, we call it credit.
But kids, where are the banks getting the money from,
and in the end, whose main hand is it? The
central bank? The central bank
puts the money in the hands of the banks, and the banks can pay this
money to consumers
as loans. That is, in the
end, we get to the central bank. And kids,
the amount of credit money is extremely important for the economy. In
current economies, credit is the
first word. I will tell you why, then,
kids, when  Let's
go back and look at the issue of credit.
Finally, we come to the central bank.
It is the central bank that determines with its own policies
what form credit or credit should take in the
economy. So the
central bank determines
what form the credit debt conditions should take. What are
the goals of the central bank?
What does the central bank do? The central bank's goal
is to advance the monetary system of the economy in such a way
that we can
achieve maximum employment, growth, and price stability. In the meetings of
central banks, especially the Federal Reserve, you
always see their statements first. In the first statement or
minutes they publish, you can see
that the Fed emphasizes that the central bank
seeks to have maximum growth in the economy
and price stability.
What does price stability mean? It means controlling inflation, meaning that there should be
no unbridled inflation in the economy. So, guys,
we understand what the goal of the central bank
is. The central bank wants economic conditions to be such
that economic growth is upward,
we have maximum economic growth,
and maximum employment, because the more employment there
is, the
higher the income of the people, and so on.  The economy
is better and price stability is another goal of the
central bank. Guys, there is a problem here,
a problem that we know as the two objectives
[music]
in economics, or you can say that the central bank's
two goals, the goal of maximum employment and
price stability, are in conflict with each other. That is, we
cannot achieve maximum employment, for example, from
economic growth of 2 to 10, and price stability also
occurs, meaning that prices do not change.
Economic growth is usually accompanied by increased inflation,
and the central bank always, guys,
has a challenge between these two goals. That is, somewhere, you can say, it
seeks to
create growth. Somewhere, it seeks to
control prices, stabilize prices, and
control inflation. These are called the two goals of the
central bank. So there is a period when we have economic growth,
very good growth, very good employment, but
guys, in this period, price stability
no longer exists. And we said that in today's economies,
when economic growth increases, inflation also
increases, and here the central bank
must focus on that and focus on
Let the price stability, not the maximum growth, be the central bank.
What are the tools? Interest rate and money supply.
We have the interest rate as the tools of the central bank.
Now let me explain to you how it
works. Guys, when we talked about interest rate,
in the previous slide we said what interest is. Interest
is the profit that you have to pay to the lender in addition to the principal.
When the central bank
lowers the interest rate in the economy, the
banks also lower the interest rate.
Now, how this system works,
maybe in a separate video I told you how
this works and how it works,
but I don't want to go into it here because it
gets a bit complicated. How the central bank
affects the interest rate of banks by lowering the interest rate. I will
probably cover it in a separate video,
but I don't want to complicate the topic here
because it is necessary to
talk about other things first. There are a number of
prerequisites. So by lowering the interest rate, the central bank
causes the banks to lower the interest rate.
Lowering the interest rate means you get
less profit for it.  The debt or loan that
you want to take from the bank must be paid.
Everyone is happy
and creates demand for loans and
credit. Credit in the
economy increases. So
by lowering the interest rate, the central bank causes credit or loans
or debt to increase in the economy. By
raising the interest rate, the central bank causes
interest rates in banks to increase. When
interest rates go higher, for example, from 2
to 5, those who applied for loans will
no longer have cheap loans like before. And here, we have less demand for
loans and credit decreases. So
the increase or decrease in interest rates has a direct relationship with the
amount of credit. Now there is a point in the middle.
Guys, by lowering the interest rate, the central bank
can affect the interest rate of banks,
but in the end, there are a number of
other factors that can
affect the bank's decision whether to lend me this money
or not. In
any case, in the end, the bank is the final decision-maker
who wants to lend the money it has in its treasury or the
money it has in its account.
Invest, hold cash,
buy bonds with it, buy stocks with it. Ultimately, the
bank itself is the decision maker, and here
issues such as lending risk, economic risk, and
these also affect the bank's decision.
Sometimes it happens. Sometimes it happens that the
central bank lowers interest rates, but
banks are reluctant to lend. For example, in
2002, when Covid happened,
banks did not lend because they did not have a clear vision of the
future economy. The
conditions
were special. The banks did not know
what was going to happen. People were scared.
Panic had happened. It was not at all clear whether
businesses would be able to continue their work
or not. People would come out of quarantine tomorrow to
go shopping and create economic growth.
So here, the risk of the Covid issue or the risk
that the borrower would not be able to pay the money had
caused the credit level to decrease. So it is
not just the central bank's problem here. There is
also economic risk,
or for example, we have the opposite. The
central bank raises interest rates, but it has a
great impact on the reduction.  There is no credit. This is
because economic growth is good now, or
the demand
for loans is very high due to increased incomes or
so on. And here, for example,
banks continue to lend,
demand is still good, and credit is
not affected. Keep these in mind. The
next tool of the central bank is the money supply. It is the
volume of money. Guys, the central bank can
print money indefinitely and
distribute this money in the economy and create economic growth.
But we said that it cannot do this
continuously and in the long run.
Because it is true that
economic growth occurs, but then we
have inflation, and inflation causes the central bank to
raise interest rates again or
to think about cornering the economy again. The
central bank cannot always support economic growth and
rationality. And when inflation increases,
if it does not address inflation and does
not target it, the economic conditions will be difficult.
So central banks can print money,
but they cannot do this continuously
because it creates inflation
when  For example, you
have 5 applicants for a car, so the
price is different from when you
have 10 applicants for a car. When the
central bank prints money, meaning it is giving money to
people, people can spend this money. The
demand in the economy increases. And as I
told you in the previous video, supply
cannot increase as quickly as demand,
and this difference causes
inflation. But one of the
central bank's tools is the money supply. The
central bank can reduce the amount of money in the economy,
and this causes the
banks to have less money anyway. And when banks
have less money, they lend that money very
cautiously and usually
raise their interest rates. They tell the person that if,
for example, a year ago you could get a loan at a rate of 5,
now because there is less money and
more applicants for loans, we are giving this loan at a rate of 8.
The bank is thinking about itself, and this
causes the amount of loans to
decrease and credit to decrease. So we
There is a direct correlation between the volume of money and the amount of credit. Similarly, an increase in the volume of
money causes credit to increase.
Bank credit increases the volume of money in the economy. There is
more money available to banks. When there is more money in
bank accounts, banks
lend it to people in order to make a profit. They compete with each other.
For
example, there is a bank with a 20% interest rate. There is a bank with a 15% interest rate.
A bank with a 20% interest rate must lower its interest rate
so that people can go and
borrow money there. And anyway, that bank has to
make that profit so that it can make a profit. Here, because money
increases in the economy, the volume of money in the economy increases.
Banks come in and lower the interest rate, and a
decrease in the interest rate can increase credit.
So the central bank
can affect the amount of credit or debt with the tools it has.
But from here on out, listen carefully
to what effect credit has on those cycles
that we talked about at the beginning of the video.
Guys, if you leave the economy alone, let's go a little further and
tell you later.  We told you guys
a while ago that we have an increase in employment growth and
inflation. We said that
with the increase in growth and employment, prices will also rise.
When prices rise, the
central bank has to raise interest rates,
reduce the money supply, and slow down the economy a
bit. Because we said that if inflation
increases too much, it will cause many problems,
especially a decrease in people's purchasing power,
and the central bank doesn't want this because
in the long run it will cause a recession, a decrease in
people's purchasing power. So what does the central bank do here? It
raises interest rates, reduces the money supply.
When this happens, credit
in the economy decreases and the
economy slows down. Now, guys,
consider that long-term debt cycle.
This is how it used to be. It's always going up and down. In the
long run, we
're growing, but what happens when this cycle
turns into something like this, something that fluctuates.
Our economic growth fluctuates in the long run. We
have a period of growth and a period of decline.
These guys...  The issue of credit in the
economy is what we are going to discuss here.
This is because you can
spend more than your income. During that
economic period, you can spend more than the money
you earn, and this causes
economic growth. When you, for example, say
your salary is 10 million, your salary is 200 million, and you can
borrow 10 million and spend it,
this causes your spending to be higher than
your income, and this causes economic growth.
Because when you
create more demand, in the economy,
your greater demand causes more sales.
More sales cause a person's income to be higher.  When it
increases, when another person's income
increases, he also increases his spending
and this economic growth
occurs. This cycle of
economic growth occurs. So it is credit
that creates these economic cycles.
Or we can say that there are periods when
you can spend more than your income. There is
also a period when you can no longer borrow
and you have to pay off those loans.
Here you have to
deduct 5 tomans from the 220 tomans that you used to receive monthly. And
here your spending becomes 155 tomans. And here you can
spend less than your income.
Or we can say that here demand decreases
and the decrease in demand causes growth to decrease.
So here we have a period of decline.
After the central bank raised the interest rate, the money supply
went down, credit
decreased, and they could
no longer
borrow in the economy. Here we enter a period of
economic growth decline. Then the economic growth declines.
This is how growth decreases.  Employment decreases,
inflation decreases, and it is controlled. The
central bank's goal was to control inflation. It reaches
this goal. It ticks. But here the
economy has weakened again and the central bank
has to support the economy. I'm telling you,
these two goals
cannot go hand in hand. Price stability
along with economic growth and employment are
not created. They are in conflict with each other. They can be
said to be mutually exclusive. The
central bank has to deal with inflation for a period and
support the economy for a period to
create economic growth or employment.
When the economy slows down, the central bank
lowers the interest rate and increases the money supply.
Everyone is happy again. People go out and take out loans.
Credit or credit increases.
Increased credit allows you to
spend more than your income. And increased spending increases
demand. Demand causes
economic growth to occur again. So
here the central bank, by increasing the money supply and
reducing the interest rate, causes credit to increase,
and finally we are back in the period.  Let's
take economic growth. This cycle
continues again. We have economic growth.
Good growth. Good employment. But here
inflation has gone up again. What does the central bank do to
control inflation? It
increases the interest rate and reduces the money supply.
Credit decreases again.
People cannot borrow. This
decrease in credit ultimately
causes economic growth to decrease. Again, we find ourselves in
a period of economic decline.
This cycle continues again. That is,
when inflation is high, the central bank
controls inflation. When it
controls inflation, it affects the
central bank's monetary policies on economic growth.
Economic growth and employment decrease. This is where it comes to
controlling economic growth and employment. Once
inflation hits, the central bank has to
control inflation again.
And we have had this cycle throughout history.
Now, I will explain it to you more and
give an example. We will go to a new slide.
Again, I want to
explain it to you in a diagram. We had a long-term
debt cycle. Sorry, we had a long-term growth cycle,
which we said.  How does this work?
In the long run, the reasons why we have economic growth
in the long run are, we said, the increase in
knowledge, technology, productivity, increasing
living standards, population growth, increased
demand, in
general, the emergence of machines, industrialization. These are
all reasons why we have growth in the
long run. Now, for example, from here on
out, it could be artificial intelligence, etc.,
traveling
to Mars, or anything else. So,
we had this long-term debt cycle. We said,
the economy is not a smooth path. It has turbulence. It has
ups and downs. Now, we want to explain
these economic wheels from
another angle. In this period, kids, the economy is
increasing economic growth that is above average. The
average, kids, is the average, this is the average,
this is our blue line. The average
economic growth in the long run,
kids, when interest rates are low,
economic growth is above average growth. Why is it
because you can, I'm telling you again, spend more than
your income,
and credit here makes it possible, meaning
you can borrow and spend more than you
have. The cycle is like this:
increasing credit, increasing credit, increasing income,
increasing demand, increasing people's self-confidence,
increasing spending, increasing prices.  Assets,
what is the increase in the price of assets? For
example,
housing, the housing market, house prices, stock market prices,
car prices. These are all in the long run in
this cycle of
increasing credit or when interest rates
are low. These all increase in price
because people have money in their hands and
go and buy these things. Demand increases.
Good economic conditions cause the stock market to grow. The
housing market grows. The market, for example,
increases in car prices. We have parallel markets that increase prices, and this increase in
prices itself increases
people's self-confidence. Consider this. Let me give you an example. In
2009,
before the stock market crashed, people
had a sense of wealth. Everyone
felt that their economic conditions had
improved. They had increased their spending. They were
living luxuriously.
What happened next? Then the stock market price decreased.
The value of the assets decreased. And
this caused the opposite to happen, reducing
people's self-confidence, and this
directly affects demand. That is,
increasing and decreasing people's self-confidence
affects their demand. For example:  Let me
tell you another example: Covid caused
people to be afraid to go out, and this
caused that demand to decrease and
ultimately economic growth to decrease. So the
first period when interest rates are low is good, the situation is going
up. But we are entering a period
when economic growth is lower than the average.
For example, you consider the average, for example,
5% in the long term, but we have an economic growth of 1%.
We are recording lower economic growth than the average.
In this
period, interest rates are high. You have to plan to
pay. You have to pay off the previous debts that you
took out. This credit that you took out here. You have to pay
this back. And this is where
economic growth decreases.
Less demand, less credit. I wrote it wrong here.
Guys, all these increases should decrease. All
these increases should decrease. Decrease in credit. Decrease in
income. Decrease in demand. Decrease in confidence.
Decrease in spending. Decrease in asset prices. For example, I
told you about the decrease in asset prices.
How did the Iranian stock market fall? Then people
lost their self-confidence. Their demand also
decreased before and after the stock market crash.
Think about how people spent.  They were so
confident about the economy.
What happened next? Here too, because they
had to repay that credit, they
spent less than their income.
And again, the cycle of interest rate cuts,
meaning interest rates, credit
comes again, and the cycle continues again.
Credit increases, income increases, demand, confidence
in oil, spending, and asset prices. Guys,
in the end, you can say that credit is a kind of borrowing
from the future. That is, in the current economies
where credit exists, there is credit. You can
spend more than your income.
Borrow from your future. Borrow from this period.
Spend more than your income here.
But again, you have to repay this. And you can
spend less than your income for a period of time.
Now, let's go back to the
first slide. Here, I'll give you an explanation about
this slide.
So what happened? Yes, let me explain here.
How does the long-term debt cycle take shape?
Guys, see in the short-
term cycles that I explained in the next slide.
Hey, we said that credit is like this: you have a  A
period, for example, here you can
spend
more than you earn,
a period of no negative, but guys,
in the long run, in the long run, the credit that is created is
much more than those negatives or intentions
that people should have. I can
tell you this way that in the long run, what
happens is that debt or credit
accumulates, it increases. We have these cycles,
this small cycle, for example, you consider
this cycle, we have an economic growth and a decline.
Here we said credit increases, here it
decreases, here the interest rate goes up, it decreases,
but this is a
greater positive than that period of credit reduction.
That is, in the long run, the
economy is constantly creating debt. It is constantly
increasing debt. That amount of
credit or credit in the economy is increasing.
We call this period the Loring period
or the period when credit increases in the economy.
And what is the long-term debt cycle? The long-
term debt cycle is the point at which
the economy collapses, meaning that the debt has
increased so much, the bubble has increased so much that the
economy no longer has traction and experiences a free fall.  It happens,
guys, that during this period, the
central bank increases the interest rate or for any
reason. For example, in 2008, when the crisis started,
we had one or two banks in America.
Or, for example, in
1930, we had a huge bubble in the
stock market. We have an event, a spark,
something that causes
people to be afraid of the economy and
have a period of decline. Guys, here, there is
so much debt. This is the point where we
said, hey, there is a lot of debt. Hey, there is a lot of debt. Hey,
in the era of leverage,
hey, there is a lot of debt.
We have a big bubble here. The stock market, for example,
records a very heavy decline for any reason.
And this causes a
very terrible cycle in the economy.
For example, what? Look, many people went during this
period and gave their property as a document
and took out a loan. The price of the property here
will fall. It will fall so much that even the
collateral that is in the banks is
no longer worth anything. That is, the bank can no longer even use that
debt as collateral by enforcing it.
People's self-confidence is low.  People can
lose their jobs, people can't
pay their debts, they can't go to work, there's
no demand, companies have to
lay off people, they reduce a lot of
their workforce, their sales are down,
they can't reduce their debts, they
have to close down part of their factories, the
consumer is under severe pressure from the banks,
and no matter how much the government comes and
lowers the interest rate, even if the interest rate goes
to zero, the kids still have no money, they
can't control this vicious cycle, and
now here we
have a series of other factors that will help them get the
economy out of this state.
So the Dilor Jing era is different from the
economic slowdown era, and
here, kids, the conditions are much more difficult. We were
in the
periods of economic slowdown, which is,
for example, from here to here, our economic growth
went from P to A, but this is a different recession.
Why am I emphasizing this so much?
Because we have to wait.
We need to know that when we are
talking about economic growth decline, they are
different from each other and very different
from the scenario that we will trade.
Now let's move on. I have prepared a few examples for you on the chart. Let's have the
examples together.
I will skip the slides
and move
on. Here we had interest rates and growth and
how inflation changes. Here
we talked about the impact of interest rates on consumer conditions.
Increase in credit. On the other hand, interest rates rise.
Decrease in
credit. During the Deal Vision period, guys, these
conditions last a long time and are very deep. For
example, if we have a period of decline, if the
growth index decreases from 1 to 20, during the
Deal Vision period, for example, it decreases from 40 to 70.
These are all the differences between the
long-term and short-term cycles. But let's go to the
charts and do the analysis. I
have the US interest rate since 1990 and the
PMI data
as an indicator of economic growth. I
want to
tell you the impact of interest rates on economic growth.
What is the impact?  Credit on
economic growth Well, here we see that guys, the
US Federal Reserve, the blue line is our interest rate, this
line is orange, our economic growth, and the number
50, 50, the red line that I drew in the middle. If we
are above it, it means we have a
period of economic growth, and if we
are below it, it means we have a period of economic growth decline,
and economic growth is lower.
Now the central bank comes and lowers the interest rate.
What does the effect of lowering the interest rate cause? It
causes economic growth. Lowering the interest rate.
What happens when the interest rate decreases?
Economic growth increases. Gross domestic product increases.
And here, lowering the interest rate increases. The
central bank comes here. At this point, it
increases the interest rate. What does
increasing the interest rate cause economic growth to decrease? The
interest rate will stay here for a while.
Of course, there is a decrease here.
Economic growth gets a little better. Here we
have normal economic growth. The interest rate
goes up again. At this point, from a rate of about four
and a half percent, we reach a
rate of about 25 and a half percent. This causes
economic growth to decrease. Economic growth decreases.
Here, the crisis of the year
We have 20,000. Economic growth has slowed down drastically. The
stock market has plummeted. The
technology bubble has deflated drastically. And here we have a
sharp decline in the US interest rate. The interest rate is
decreasing. It reaches the 1D range. And
for these guys, what is it for?
To support the economy, the
central bank lowers the interest rate.
Economic growth is good. Inflation is probably going
up here. The central bank will start
raising interest rates from 204 to 207.
We are raising interest rates. Economic growth is
decreasing.
After the crisis of 2028, the central bank
will lower the interest rate to the 0 range. The
interest rate is zero. Now, the fact that the interest rate is
zero does not mean that banks are
lending at the Safad rate. Usually, this interest rate that the
central bank is setting is the interbank interest rate
and the reverse repo rate. I will
apologize for this mechanism in a separate video in future videos. In a
separate video, I will explain it to you completely. It is a
one-hour video on its own.
Banks usually lend at a higher rate.
Consider this: it is zero
percent.  It doesn't mean you go to the bank and the
bank tells you to come and take money and
pay me back in, say, 10 years. We don't
have anything like that. In
economies, interest rates are drastically reduced.
To support the economy, in the
2008 financial crisis, interest rates remain zero for several years so that the
economy can recover. The economy
recovers. Economic growth.
Here
again, we have inflation. We have
economic growth. The central bank raises interest rates.
Help me and it causes economic growth to
decrease. Then Covid comes and it messes everything up. The
central bank lowers interest rates again.
Lowering interest rates causes growth to
increase and we have a good period in
2021. Then inflation reaches its peak. The
central bank raises interest rates.
Now let's go to the next slide and have inflation.
Next to the interest rate, well here we see
that
inflation has decreased. After the
central bank had high interest rates here,
inflation has decreased and decreased.
Inflation is our red line.
Well, the central bank has decreased its term and lowered the interest rate.
Lowering the interest rate has
caused inflation to increase a little.  But not so much
that the central bank wants to raise interest rates. We
had a period where inflation was relatively stable. The
central bank
lowered interest rates in 2000 after the bursting of the technology bubble.
Here, kids, inflation has also decreased
with interest rates. Why can we say that inflation is
decreasing here, kids? It means that
economic growth has decreased, meaning that consumption has decreased so much
that price inflation has also decreased. But
inflation has started to increase for a while, and the
central bank has been forced to increase interest rates. The
increase in interest rates has
caused economic growth and inflation to decrease again.
Inflation comes down, and the
central bank cuts interest rates to support the economy in 2008,
and then inflation
increases. Here, inflation is above the
233 range. It becomes 3. Here,
inflation is above 3. The
central bank starts raising interest rates
to control inflation. It controls inflation, but
economic growth also decreases with it, as we saw in the previous slide.
And Covid comes and messes
everything up. The central bank
lowers interest rates again.  Inflation will
increase sharply in 2022 and the central bank
will have to raise the interest rate. Guys,
inflation affects the central bank's decision, and it
is the central bank that affects inflation by
controlling the volume of money and liquidity and the interest rate in general.
That is, it
is a two-way relationship. One does not affect the other.
Both are having an effect. Now about the
unemployment rate, the effect of the interest rate on unemployment. The
interest rate reduction.
And let's start from the end this time. Let's say in 2020-21, the
central bank lowered its interest rate due to
Covid. Let's say what happened to Covid. The unemployment rate
increased sharply. People left their jobs.
Many came and stayed home. The
central bank supported the economy and this caused the
unemployment rate to decrease. Here, I will
tell you what the unemployment rate is. What percentage of the
population is looking for work and is unemployed? This
means that this rate that increases
is bad for the economy and the lower it is, the
better. The unemployment rate means that people
are working and the number of unemployed has decreased. That is,
here, for example, the rate  Our unemployment rate is 8.5
percent, meaning 3.5 percent of the population
looking for work is unemployed. The rest are working. So
after the central bank
lowered the interest rate,
employment grew and the unemployment rate
reached a minimum. And then, with the increase in interest rates, we will
probably see an increase in the unemployed. But
guys,
unemployment is the last link that is affected
and it lags behind and
follows changes in interest rates, growth, and
inflation. You see here, the
interest rate increased, and after one or two
years, the unemployment rate increased.
Here, for example, the interest rate decreased, and
after two or three years, the unemployment rate was affected.
Or we
can
have other examples, for example, here, the interest rate
increased, and then we had an increase in the unemployment rate.
Now, I will have a separate video again.
These are all topics that
need to be discussed in more detail. It is necessary for you to understand the
basic topics
and these topics that are very important.
You guys, we will have a
much easier job. In the
following, I will explain to you in a full video that the
impact of economic data
From growth to inflation and employment,
how do they change, how do they
affect each other? Why is employment what we
call data that ultimately affects?
Why is economic growth, for example, affected quickly?
Which parts are affected first?
How do we need to understand
what cycle we
are in? Which ones change? It signals that,
for example, the unemployment rate and inflation, etc. are also going to
change. This
will be a separate, one-hour video, and
we will cover it in more detail. I hope it was useful to you.
This was the fourth part, in which we
added the topic of credit, the effect of the central bank's interest rate, the
volume of central bank money
on the economy
and its changes. In the next videos, we
want to take this topic to a certain point. Now, we have reached a certain point in the
next videos. I want to
talk a little about financial markets and the characteristics of different assets,
and in addition to the topic of
economic cycles, why do these assets react in different cycles? We are
gradually entering into topics that directly affect
trading.  We hope it was
useful for you. If this
educational set has helped
you
and been able to
help you in the fundamentals topic,
share this set with others and
introduce this set to your friends. The
fundamentals topic has not been covered much in the past. There has been no
such
training. Many
friends have taken the trouble to prepare the training, but I
tried to tell you in a very simple language so that they will be
interested. The fundamentals topic
is really simple. There is nothing special.
Just by practicing and repeating a little bit
and thinking about what is happening in
the economy, you can understand the fundamentals. You
think about it, repeat it,
study the different wheels a little,
read a little, for example, what
happened in the United States in 2008, etc. Or, for example,
if you
are active in the Iranian stock market, you
can even analyze the Iranian economy with
these. You can see that these
topics are very simple and
you can acquire this knowledge through repetition.
Use fundamental science and technical knowledge alongside it
to have the best performance in the market.
So if this  If you found the collection useful,
share it with others. Introduce it to your friends.
These slides and
the things I'm using are
all my own creations. This chart
you see is all mine. I went looking for it myself and put the interest rate on the
unemployment rate, for example. I
prepared different slides for you.
This topic of preparing slides and these took a lot of
time to be able to prepare something
that could convey to you in the simplest and clearest way possible
what I want to say. I've
also put my Instagram and Telegram IDs below for you.
You can
follow my Instagram. If you
have any questions, send a message to my Telegram ID. You
will be added to the group and you can
get your question answered there. I hope it was
useful for you. Until the next episode,
goodbye.